Finding Aid for YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit, Metropolitan Offices records, 1877-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit, Metropolitan Offices records 1877-2012
YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit. Metropolitan Offices.
90124 Bk 2
Branch of the YMCA; Annual reports, clippings, correspondence, financial records, minutes of meetings, photographs, press releases, published materials, rosters, and scrapbooks; also includes collected branch records for the Railroad branch, 1877-1890, and the Downtown branch, 1890-1909; and publication, Detroit Young Men, 1911-1922.
11 linear feet in 13 boxes
21 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated in December 1989 by the Metropolitan Offices of the YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit (Donor no. 7754 ) through Robert Davis, president of the YMCA's Metropolitan Offices. Periodic additions have been received.
The record group is open to research.
The Metropolitan Offices of the YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit were established in 1921 to oversee the operations of the various YMCA branches in Detroit and to serve as liaison between these branches and the state and national offices of the YMCA. Until the formal establishment of these offices these tasks were executed by the officers of the downtown branch of the Detroit YMCA. The Detroit YMCA traces its origins to efforts made in 1852 and 1858 to organize those interested in improving "the spiritual and mental condition of young men." Neither of these efforts were sustained. After the Civil War, in the midst of a national resurgence of the YMCA, the Detroit YMCA was re-established in 1867 with a mission expanded to include physical and social elements of man's existence. This version of the Detroit YMCA was able to sustain and expand its efforts in the community by building new facilities, increasing membership, raising its profile locally, and expanding its programs.
With a membership of nearly one thousand, and no access to a suitable building, the Detroit YMCA underwrote the building of the city's first YMCA building in 1887. This structure at Griswold and Grand River contained reading rooms, a library, a plunge, and a gymnasium. It adequately served the needs of local members for nearly twenty years. At the same time, the needs of railroad workers passing through Detroit were met at the "Railroad Y" on the south side of town. As Detroit's population grew, the demand for and use of the YMCA facilities outstripped the existing plant. In May 1906, with membership breaching three thousand, the Detroit YMCA raised over $500,000 to erect a new building. In 1909, the new Downtown YMCA opened at the corner of Witherell and Adams. This building contained reading rooms, a library, two gymnasiums (one for men and one for boys), a swimming pool, five floors of residence rooms, handball courts, and administrative office space.
From 1910 to 1930 the population of Detroit trebled. The growth in YMCA membership more than matched the city's rapid population growth, moving from just under four thousand in 1910 to fourteen thousand in 1930. It was immediately clear that the Downtown YMCA building would be unable to provide convenient access to its facilities to all interested men. The answer lay in the opening of six neighborhood branches of the YMCA between 1916 and 1924: Highland Park, Western, Fisher, St. Antoine, Mack Avenue, and Hannan. The formation of these branches precipitated the formal creation of the Metropolitan Offices of the Detroit YMCA to handle business which had formerly been dealt with by the downtown branch officers. A five million dollar fund raising drive was held in May 1925 in order to finance the building of facilities for each of the branches. The success of this drive was assured by the generosity of several prominent Detroit families, among them the Fords, Dodges, Kresges, Fishers, and Hannans, who readily underwrote efforts to expand YMCA influence.
The 1930s were grim and difficult times for both the city of Detroit and the YMCA. The shattered local economy could not sustain the growth of the YMCA generated by the boom times of the 1920s. Retrenchment led to the closing of the Hamtramck branch which had opened in 1928 and forced the curtailing of staff and operations in all branches. It was not until World War II that the Detroit YMCA recovered the momentum for growth which it enjoyed in the 1920s. This time the nexus of development was suburban Detroit as the YMCA continued to build in regions of population growth. The Wyandotte, Birmingham, Royal Oak, Dearborn, and Northwest YMCA buildings were all completed between 1944 and 1950. Membership in metropolitan YMCAs topped thirty thousand by 1950; the future looked rosy. Unfortunately for the St. Antoine branch, the growth and prosperity of the suburban branches did not guarantee the continued existence of the inner city branch reserved for Blacks. Given the changing social climate regarding segregated facilities, the reshaping of inner cities by urban renewal and highways, and the economic difficulties of St. Antoine, the Metropolitan Detroit YMCA opted to close this branch in 1960. Wayne-Westland branch was established in the early 1960s, experienced two building campaigns but closed in 2003.
The YMCA is more than the sum of expanding membership and new buildings; its commitment to improving the mental, spiritual, social, and physical aspects of men is manifested through its programs. While many of these programs changed over time, the spiritual development of members remained a central feature at the core of the religious department of the YMCA. The mental condition of young men was tended to through lectures during the nineteenth century and through formal programs and institutions, especially the Detroit Institute of Technology, in the twentieth century. The social development of boys and young men was attended to by departments within the YMCA created to assure the inculcation of Christian ideals at an early age. Summer camps at Camp Nissokone (on Van Etten Lake near Oscoda) and Camp Ohiyesa (on Fish Lake near Clyde) were founded in the 1910s to further YMCA ideals in the great outdoors. The physical development was encouraged not only through the well appointed buildings, but through programs of physical education and the formation of leagues. In practice the spiritual, mental, social, and physical aspects of man were closely linked so that programs developed by the YMCA affected all four attributes.
The records of the Metropolitan Offices of the YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit consist of annual reports, correspondence, financial materials, minutes (Secretary's records), photographs, published brochures and pamphlets, and scrapbooks. The materials document, somewhat unevenly, the efforts of the YMCA to tend to the spiritual, physical, and social needs of the young men in Detroit. The strengths of this record group are in its minutes (Secretary's records) and photographs, each of which provides detailed and telling insight into the development of Detroit and the YMCA from the nineteenth century to 2006. The scrapbooks created by the YMCA, 1936-1973, are also of interest in that they accurately reflect all newspaper coverage of YMCA events and activities for this decade.
The records have been arranged in four series: Administration, Secretary's Records, Visual Materials, and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.); Detroit young men; Physical fitness.; YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit.; YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit. Metropolitan Offices.; Young Men's Christian Associations.; Youth--Religious life.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Michigan.; Americanization.; Auburn Hills (Mich.)--Buildings.; Banjos.; Basketball.; Birmingham (Mich.)--Buildings.; Broadcasting.; Buildings--Michigan.; Camps--Michigan.; Children.; Clubhouses.; Dearborn (Mich.)--Buildings.; Detroit (Mich.)--Buildings.; Eastpointe (Mich.)--Buildings.; Highland Park (Mich.)--Buildings.; Immigrants.; Laborers.; Maltese Americans--Michigan.; Minstrel shows.; Physical fitness.; Recreation.; Royal Oak (Mich.)--Buildings.; Swimming.; Table tennis.; World War, 1914-1918.; Young Men's Christian Associations.; Youth--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Administration
  The Administration series consists of three subseries: A.G. Studer and R. Elliott files; R. Adelberg files; and Topical files.
  - A.G. Studer and R. Elliott files 1879-1953
    This subseries consists of those materials pulled together by the general secretary, A.G. Studer, and the director of public relations, Russell Elliott. The records comprise eight linear inches and begin with Studer's published history of the Detroit YMCA. Other materials in this subseries are arranged alphabetically by type of record. The annual reports provide quick access to data on membership, programs, and financial operations.
    - History One Hundred Years with Youth, 1952 (Box 1)
    - Annual reports 1912-1952
      - 1912, 1915-1919 (Box 1)
      - 1920, 1923-1927, 1929 (Box 1)
      - 1930-1935 (Box 1)
      - 1937-1942 (Box 1)
      - 1947 (Branches only) (Box 1)
      - 1948 (Branches only) (Box 1)
      - 1949 (Branches only) (Box 1)
      - 1950 (Box 1)
      - 1952 (Box 1)
    - Brochures and pamphlets 1879-1953
      - 1879-1904 (Box 1)
      - 1906-1909 (Box 1)
        (includes building of Downtown YMCA)
      - 1909-1919 (Box 1)
        (includes Survey of the Boyhood of Detroit, 1909)
      - 1920-1934 (Box 1)
        (includes Salesman's Handbook 1925)
      - 1936-1940 (Box 1)
      - Physical Education Congress 1938 (Box 1)
      - 1946-1953 (Box 1)
    - Financial 1909-1942
      - Correspondence re Laurence estate 1919-1936 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous 1909-1942 (Box 1)
  - R. Adelberg 1948-1968, 1965-1966
    This subseries consists of Ray Adelberg's materials generated while acting as director of public relations in the mid 1960s. The nine folders in this subseries are arranged alphabetically.
    - Branches newsletter 1965 (Box 1)
    - Business operations unit 1965 (Box 1)
    - Executive staff group 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - Gang problem 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - Health and physical education commission 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - President's leadership conference 1966 (Box 1)
    - Program development study 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - Radio spots 1948-1960 (Box 1)
    - State YMCA personnel and policy handbooks 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Topical
    The Topical files concerns anniversary celebrations and annual reports from 1990 through the second decade of the twenty-first century. The subseries includes some materials from the service of Robert Davis, secretary in the 1970s, John Copeland, Executive Director of the St. Antoine Branch in the 1950s and Vice-President of Public Relations and Urban Affairs in the 1970s, and Reid S. Thebault, CEO in the 1990s through 2003; and a history entitled YMCA in America, 1851-2001. Also included in this subseries is the history and land acquisition file for the Wayne-Westland branch, which closed in 2003. A history of the branch is included as well as a small number of photos. This subseries also includes press releases, clippings, brochures and pamphlets, board and committee rosters, reports from Camps Ohiyesa and Nissokone, and files relating to the Dearborn, Wayne-Westland, and Greater Warren Family YMCAs.
    - Anniversaries
      - 125th Anniversary Celebration of YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit 1978 (Box 2)
      - 125th Anniversary of Black YMCA, Program Manual 1978 (Box 2)
      - 150th Anniversary of YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit 2002 (Box 2)
    - Annual meetings
      - Programs 1997-2012 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
      - Convention script and fund-raising material 2007 (Box 2)
      - Convention script 2008 (Box 2)
      - Convention script and miscellaneous material 2011-2012 (Box 2)
    - Annual Reports 1990-2011 (some gaps) (Box 2)
    - Board rosters (metro and branch) 1998-1999 (Box 2)
    - Boll Family YMCA Publicity 2005-2006 (Box 2)
    - Brochures and pamphlets 1970s-2009 (scattered), 2 folders (Box 2)
      (includes The Challenge to Detroit, 1970s)
    - Brochures and pamphlets (Camps) 1937-2008 (scattered, Camps Nissokone, Ohiyesa, Hiyo-went-ha, Man-go-tah-see, and Women's Fitness) (Box 2)
      (see also oversize brochure in box 10)
    - Building Strong Kids 1994 (Box 2)
    - Camp Ohiyesa
      - Camp Information 1930-1983 (scattered) (Box 2)
      - History (Box 2)
      - Manual 1937 (Box 2)
      - Reports 1929, 1931, 1938, 1944, 1945, 1946, 1958, 1964, undated (Box 2)
    - Camp Nissokone
      - Report 1925 (Box 2)
      - Financial Analysis of Proposed 150 site Recreational Vehicle Campground at Camp Nissokone 1973 (Box 2)
    - Clippings circa 1966-1998, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - Clippings, newsletters, and publications (miscellaneous) 1927-1947, undated (Box 11)
    - Committee commission and rosters (Box 11)
    - Consecration of John and Marlene Boll Family 2005 (Box 11)
    - Copeland, John 1952-1979 and undated (Box 11)
    - Correspondence regarding the establishment of a camp in the Pickerel River District 1946, 1948 (Box 11)
    - Dearborn YMCA
      - Membership Drive
        - Correspondence, clippings, and other materials 1957 (Box 11)
        - Photographs used in the campaign (Box 11)
          (include events featuring Van Patrick and Mayor Orville Hubbard; also activities at the Y)
      - Dearborn YMCA News 1958-1960 (Box 11)
    - Detroit Events Pamphlets 2005-2006 (Box 11)
    - Event Programs 1987-2006 (Box 11)
    - Golf Classic
      - 1995-2010 (Box 11)
      - 2011-2012 (Box 11)
    - Greater Warren Family YMCA
      - Mission statement and historical information 1982, 1994 (Box 11)
      - Capital campaign / new building 1982 (Box 11)
    - Heritage Club 1978, 2011 (Box 11)
    - Historical materials (Box 11)
    - "In the News" (articles about the YMCA) 1997-1999 (Box 11)
    - Lawrence, Leonard -- financial receipts, etc. circa 1908 (Box 11)
    - Metropolitan Detroit Building Fund (MDBF) 1955-1959
      - Contracts 1955 (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous 1955 (Box 11)
      - Presentations 1959 (Box 11)
    - Minority Achievers Letters 2003, undated (Box 11)
    - New North Oakland Family YMCA prospectus undated (Box 11)
    - North Oakland County YMCA
      - Feasibility study 1994 (Box 11)
      - Capital campaign manual circa 2000 (Box 11)
    - Press release distribution update 1998 (Box 12)
    - Press releases 1996-1999, 11 folders (Box 12)
    - Programs (miscellaneous) 1927, 1986 (Box 12)
    - Report: Opportunities in Downtown Detroit for the YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit January 13, 1999 (Box 12)
      (also includes related national study "Economic & Social Benefits of YMCAs, 1997)
    - Residence Management for a Young Men's Christian Association, 1977 (Box 12)
    - Strong Kids Campaign (Heart of the Y, Power of the Y) 2011 (Box 12)
    - United Foundation Agreement 1966 (Box 12)
    - Vision 2000 capital campaign for Farmington Area YMCA (Box 12)
    - Ward Leaders Club and Ward Alumni Leaders Club 1929, 1944, 1947, undated (Box 12)
    - Wayne-Westland Branch 1943-2001, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Western Branch YMCA Groundbreaking 1927 (Box 12)
    - YMCA Fund Drive articles 1960-1967 (Box 12)
    - YMCA Leadership/Strategic Planning (Box 12)
- Secretary's Records (including Detroit Young Men), 1877-1975
  The Secretary's Records (including Detroit Young Men) (1877-1975) series comprises over two linear feet of materials and primarily consists of the minutes of the executive board of the Metropolitan Offices of the YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit from 1921 to 1975. The materials created before 1921 consist of the minutes of the Railroad branch from 1877 to 1890, the minutes of the downtown branch of the Detroit YMCA from 1890 to 1909, and the publication, Detroit Young Men, for the years 1911 to 1922. These earlier records are treated as the official minutes and historical record by the present Metropolitan Offices of the YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit, so they are included in this series. These Secretary's records provide an excellent week-by-week insight into the operations of the Detroit YMCA beginning in the early 1890s. They also serve to illuminate the changing faces of the city of Detroit. Of special interest are the minutes describing the closing of the St. Antoine branch of the YMCA. This branch had served as the "colored Y" from its inception in 1919, but changing attitudes, limited funds, and urban renewal prompted its closing in 1960. The Bentley Historical Library has copies of the Secretary's records after 1921, the originals are retained by the Metropolitan Offices of the YMCA of Metropolitan Detroit.
  - Railroad branch minutes 1877-1890 (Box 3)
  - Secretary's records 1890-1909
    - 1890-1896, 1 volumes (Box 3)
    - 1896-1903, 1 volumes (Box 3)
    - Loose leaves from 1890-1896, 1896-1903 (Box 4)
    - 1904-1909, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Detroit Young Men 1911-1922
    - Volume 9 1911-1912 (Box 4)
    - Volumes 11-17 1913-1920 (Box 4)
    - Volume 19 1921-1922 (Box 4)
    - Volume 24 no.33 and Volume 3 no.21 1927, 1930 (Box 4)
  - Secretary's records 1921-1975
    - 1921-1924 (Box 4)
    - 1925-1926 (Box 4)
    - 1927-March 1930 (Box 4)
    - April 1930-April 9, 1934 (Box 4)
    - April 15, 1934-March 1939 (Box 4)
    - April 1939-January 1945 (Box 5)
    - February 1945-May 1949 (Box 5)
    - June 1949-January 1954 (Box 5)
    - April 1954-April 1957 (Box 5)
    - April 1957-June 1959 (Box 5)
    - re closing of St. Antoine branch 1957-1960 (Box 5)
    - October 1959-May 1961 (Box 5)
    - June 1961-April 1963 (Box 5)
    - July 1963-April 1965 (Box 5)
    - June 1965-September 1966 (Box 5)
    - February 1967-June 1968 (Box 5)
    - September 1968-January 1970 (Box 5)
    - April 1970-April 1971 (Box 5)
    - June 1971-June 1972 (Box 6)
    - September 1972-October 1973 (Box 6)
    - January 1974-January 1975 (Box 6)
- Visual materials
  The Visual Materials series is divided into CD-ROMs, videotapes. and photographs.
  - CD-ROMs
    - Downtown Family YMCA/Boll Family YMCA beam signing/topping off 2004, 2 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 6)
    - Legacy golf classic 2003, 5 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 6)
      (includes photographs and miscellaneous publicity files)
  - Videotapes
    - Indian guide, 1" videotape (Box 6)
  - Photographs
    Photographs is divided into: Albums/Scrapbooks, 1900-1925; Public Relations reference file, 1898-2002; Public Relations reference file, 1976-2005; and Miscellaneous and general. The series comprises about two linear feet of materials and is a rich source of visual images of Detroit, the activities at the various branches of the YMCA, and the YMCA summer camps.
    - Albums/Scrapbooks 1900-1925
      Albums/Scrapbooks, 1900-1925, contains twelve scrapbooks of photographs. These scrapbooks are identified and arranged in rough chronological order. Of special note are: the City Industrial scrapbook which shows outreach efforts made to industrial workers and English language courses; the International Convention of 1919 which provides detailed documentation of this conference hosted by the Detroit YMCA; and the Camps scrapbooks that reveal the day-to-day activities of the Detroit YMCA's summer camps during their early years.
      - Camping, swimming, and conferences 1900-1903 (Box 6)
      - Detroit YMCA leaders 1909 (Box 6)
      - City industrial department 1918-1920s (Box 6)
        (includes photos of laborers, English language classes for Maltese-Americans)
      - 40th International Convention 1919 (Box 6)
      - Camp McRae (summer camp) 1913 (Box 6)
      - Camp Nissokone (summer camp) 1919-1922, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - Camp Nissokone (summer camp) 1922-1925, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Public Relations reference file 1898-1966
      In the Public Relations reference file, 1898-1966, photographs remain in the alphabetical arrangement devised by the public relations department, a scheme based on types of activity, program names, general descriptions such as "leaders" and "buildings," and quite specific celebrations. The photographs in this subseries were evidently used by the public relations department in the course of preparing brochures and publications.
      - Adult fellowship circa 1940-1950s (Box 7)
      - Annual Dinner 1961 (Box 7)
      - Annual Meeting 1964 (Box 7)
      - Awards 1938-1960 (Box 7)
      - Badminton 1938-1940s (Box 7)
      - Banjo club circa 1935-1940s (Box 7)
        (includes blackface program)
      - Basketball 1940s-1950s (Box 7)
      - Boys Club building (interiors) circa 1900-1910s (Box 7)
      - Boys Club 1898-1910 (Box 7)
      - Boys' hobbies 1938-1950 (Box 7)
      - Buildings (exteriors) circa 1900-1966 (Box 7)
        (see also oversize box 10)
      - Camp Nissokone undated (Box 7)
      - Camp Ohiyesa, from 1927 undated (Box 7)
      - Detroit's 250th anniversary (YMCA show) 1951 (Box 7)
      - Downtown branch 50th anniversary 1959 (Box 7)
      - Hi-Y Clubs 1950s (Box 7)
      - Leaders (Detroit) 1898-1960, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Leaders (National) circa 1898-1930s (Box 7)
      - Like Now: for supporting youth (Box 7)
      - Negatives 1938-1940s (Box 7)
      - Negatives undated (Box 7)
      - Pageants 1935-1941
        - "On to '44" 1941 (Box 7)
        - "Youth on the March" 1935 (Box 7)
      - Physical fitness circa 1905-1958 (Box 7)
      - Physical fitness exhibition circa 1960 (Box 7)
      - Ping Pong circa 1920s-1941 (Box 7)
      - Pontiac YMCA 1952-1954 (Box 7)
      - Radio broadcasting 1938-1941 (Box 7)
      - Slides (Box 7)
      - Springfield College exhibition team 1935-1939 (Box 7)
      - St. Antoine branch 1926-1960 (Black branch) (Box 7)
      - State church league championships 1948-1959 (Box 7)
      - Sundry historical photos 1928-1962 (Box 7)
      - World War I, Young Men in France 1917-1918 (Box 7)
    - Public Relations Reference File 1976-2005, undated
      The Public Relations reference file, 1976-2005, is divided between Events listed chronologically and Topical. Large Groups and Portraits include some photos of Stanley Kresge and his wife, Dorothy, long-term supporters of the YMCA. The Ford family had a historic link with the YMCA through Henry Ford Sr. who taught at the YMCA in the 1890s. Some YMCA events were hosted at the historic Ford home in Grosse Pointe. The gradual change in leadership, becoming more inclusive of the Black community in Detroit, can be seen over the years in this photographic history.
      - Events, in chronological order
        - Large and small groups (Box 8)
        - Centennial Parade Rochester YMCA 1976 (Box 8)
        - Pinewood Derby 1977 (Box 8)
        - Celebrity Roast Pontiac YMCA 1981 (Box 8)
        - Damon Keith Awards 1986, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Kid's Olympics 1992 (Box 8)
        - Employee Recognition Dinner 1993 (Box 8)
        - Minority Achievers 1993, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Annual Meetings 1993, 1996-1997, 2003, 3 folders (Box 8)
        - Golden Oldies Awards 1997 (Box 8)
        - Chairman's Club 1998 (Box 8)
        - Branch photos 1998-1999 (Box 8)
        - Building Campaign and Ground breaking 2003 (Box 8)
        - Beam Topping, Boll YMCA (Box 8)
      - Topical
        - Activities with children (Box 8)
        - Annual meeting conducted on the Detroit People Mover 2005 (Box 8)
        - Annual Report photos (Box 8)
        - Arts and Humanities 1998 (Box 8)
        - Camp activities (Box 8)
        - Chandler Park 1999 (Box 8)
        - Dearborn YMCA activities and events (Box 8)
        - International Men's Club, Fisher Detroit, 4 folders (Box 8)
        - Invest in Youth (Box 8)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
        - North Oakland Family YMCA, views of building model (Box 8)